I still have no idea why the [__]
chicken dish is named after him, but
there you go.
General Tso's chicken, a traditional,
authentic, not Chinese dish. But, it
gives us a great opportunity to talk
about some history that I personally am
very, very interested in. For example,
the topic that shouldn't be touched of
Xinjiang, the legal rebellion, the
Dungan Revolt, as well as the actual
General Tso Tsung-tang. If we're being
honest, is the reason it's called
Xinjiang, which just means the new
frontier. We'll talk about all that
later. So, General Tso's chicken, what
is it? Well, it is, put simply, fried
chicken covered in jizzy sauce, which is
the format of a lot of North
Americanized Chinese food, just fried
pieces of protein, you spend all day
trying to make it crispy, and then you
uncrispen it in a sauce. This one is
acid and chili forward, or is meant to
be, because it was invented by a chef
who was originally born in Hunan. So,
let's start with the recipe, and then
while we're prepping, we can talk about
the [__] okay? It's called General
Tso's chicken. Now, I want to be frank
and clear right now that it has, at the
very best, a infinitesimally tangential
relationship to the man himself. The
only reason it's called General Tso's
chicken, and from now on, I want you to
be able to pronounce the guy's actual
name, Tso Tsung-tang, General Left. The
only reason it's called this is because
the general was also born in the Hunan
province. That's the only reason. One of
the greatest generals, if not the
greatest general of the failing late
Qing Dynasty, was a man born in the
Hunan province, and the chef was also
born in the Hunan province. So, he named
it in honor of this imperial general,
for whatever the [__] reason. But, I
have chopped ginger and garlic to your
heart's content, and some dried chilies.
The ratio of these are all up to you. If
you had to bend my arm, I would say 20 g
garlic, 10 to 15 g ginger, and about 20
dry chilies here. Here I have 300 g of
diced up chicken thigh, into which goes
one egg, at which point we season with
soy sauce, sesame oil, and [music]
cooking wine by the ratio of your
choice, or if you consult our previous
episode, you just use my cocktail of
brown liquids here, which makes Chinese
cookery so god damn easy. And you go in
there, and you molest to your heart's
content. Finger and swish until you feel
embarrassed at what you're doing to this
chicken. So, this is what it's going to
look like. A lot of liquid inside this
batter, but that's okay, because it is
going to become our batter and not just
the marinade. So, whereas in most
[music] western forms of cookery, the
general thesis is to create a bowl of
flavorful lube, put my meat inside, wait
for [__] ever. Overnight is best, but
[music] 4 hours in the fridge. And then
we take our protein out and [__] dump
our money down the sink, and then take
three whole separate containers of three
separate ingredients, egg, flour, and
bread crumb, and do a [__] morris
dance, like good morning Mr. Magpie,
across my counter [__] everything up,
THEN THROW MY EGG, FLOUR, and bread
crumb down into the drain again, to
messily fry my big pieces of meat. Or I
can just do this, where I force the
flavor in with my hand quickly, and then
with the extra liquid I build my batter
around the meat, thus throwing nothing
away. 10 white peppers in here? White
pepper is what we're doing. White
pepper. Cool. If you like it sweet, you
may add more sugar. I barely ever do
like it sweet, so this is how much. And
then in here goes some baking powder,
which is optional, but it will sort of
tenderize the chicken, because it is
slightly alkali, much like how baking
soda will, but beyond that, it will also
help the batter
puff up when it hits the oil, all right?
So, I like to put my baking powder in
first, then mixy mixy mixy mixy mix mix
mix. Comment, like, subscribe. From
here, you're going to want to set your
stove to the designated temperature.
Instead of recipe saying fry at a low
temperature than fry at a high
temperature, I prefer to actually give
you numbers. So, 145 is how I like my
first fry, and then we're going to fry
it again at a second temperature to
recrispen it. This is my all-purpose
mixed animal fat that I always have in
my fridge for frying purposes. This dish
was originally invented by what's his
name? Can you find it?
>> [laughter]
>> So, Peng Chang Kuei is his actual name.
1918 or 1919, the man was born. At 13,
he ran away from his home to go be an
apprentice for a famous Hunan chef. Like
he's like the Marco Pierre White of
World War I China, of post-imperial
China. And then after that, he became a
guo yan chu shi for the nationalists.
Guo yan chu shi means like a national
banquet chef. So, guo yan is essentially
considered our zenith of culinary
excellence, the equivalent to Michel
Roux Jr. cook cooking for President
Mitterrand at the presidential palace or
cooking for the queen. It's It's the
exact same idea, right? That's the
zenith of being a cook in China. In
1949, right before we were liberated,
sorry, right before their plans for the
country didn't work out, the
nationalists fled to Taiwan. Mr. Peng
went with them. It was during thisish
time that he developed his dish. He went
to Taiwan with everybody to serve as a
chef. And then from there, he made roads
to America, I think New York, where he
modified this dish, General Tso's
Chicken, to have more sugar in it and
vinegar in it for that sweet and sour
vibe to account for the American tastes.
And then he took back the chilies, which
is why it became an American Chinese
food classic alongside crab rangoon and
chop suey, whatever the [__] those mean.
And the reason he became so popular was
Henry Kissinger was actually one of his
regulars in America at the time. He
would go and eat there a lot, so that
made him famous.
The '80s, he went back to Taiwan and
opened up a chain of restaurants and
worked until he died in 2016. So, he's
been around for a long time. 老先生 一直 做到
臨終 為止。
That's the story of General Tso's
chicken. Do you guys want to hear about
General Tso himself?
Oh, by the way, this is maybe 20 g of
cornstarch, but the recipe isn't really
that important because it also depends
on how wet your chicken is. Just keep on
adding until it looks like there's a
batter around your chicken. Unless
you're super experienced like I, I
recommend you start with little bits.
And mix until you get the texture you
want. But this is roughly what you're
looking for. Right? See how all of our
seasoning is not going to waste. It's
become part of the batter. Yeah? So,
this is a no waste way to cook. Yeah,
instead of throwing all your money down
the drain. Oh, I also have like one
little leftover onion here and I can cut
it into super American Chinese food
pieces. Yep. When your oil is up to
temp, add it in one piece at a time.
Feel free to break it up with your
spatula. And this is where the magic
happens. All this batter, scrape it
directly into the oil as part of a dish.
Because if we're honest, we're eating
this dish because of the crispy batter.
We're not here to have healthy food.
Yeah? All right. So, the man was born in
1814 in Hunan. To an impoverished Hunan
if we're being honest because the South
wasn't considered a very luxurious place
to live during the late Qing Dynasty or
even historically in China, but we'll
get to that in another episode. He was
famously [__] at school. He failed the
the state exam seven times, I think. And
then he just decided to be self-taught.
He just started to self-teach. And
through a series of fortunate and
unfortunate events, he started becoming
a military leader. He showed promise. He
led a volunteer force of 5,000 men
called the Chu Army. Let me fry this up
first. What I want is what I get. So,
after a gentle fry at the first
temperature for about 3 minutes until
your chicken's most of the way cooked,
you strain it out and then we can
prepare the wok for the second fry at
the very very high temperature.
Let it drain of its fat first.
Put that off to the side. Let it rest.
What are some other cool things about
him? Oh, he put down the peace
rebellion, the Taiping rebellion. So, he
put down the Taiping rebellion. He led
the two army of 5,000 volunteer forces.
And then he was appointed the
governor-general of Fujian and Zhejiang.
So, he was Ming Jia Zong Du. He was also
the first person to formally create a
shipyard that created modern navy for
the Qing army. He was a good leader. He
was smart. So, why is it called Xinjiang
the elephant in the room? It's called
Xinjiang because the word Xinjiang means
new frontier. Before it was called new
frontier, it was a [__] mishmash. In the
mid-1800s, there was this thing called
the Great Game. The Great Game was this
fuckboy mind game between the British
and the Russians for who would be the
big daddy of Central Asia. And he was
given the choice, both fortunately and
unfortunately, to make a decision.
What's more important? [__] with the
Japanese and having a foothold in the
Pacific or holding our western frontier
and getting back that land from the
Russians. Because in one generation, the
Russians will be at my neck. The
Japanese will be two generations from me
after I've long been dead. So, he made
that decision for his career and for his
country at the time to be given the task
of re-consolidating
the western frontier. Now, this is weird
because this part of history I have to
be very I'm not going to use the word
careful, but sensitive to everybody
involved. Cuz for better or for worse,
everybody is subject and victim to their
own flavors of propaganda and narrative
in their countries of origin, birth, and
residence. So, I want to be indeed
sensitive to everybody listening to this
story in the sense that I want you to
have the facts as I have them with as
little coloration as possible. So, the
rebellion started in Shaanxi, Ningxia,
Gansu, which is where all of our Muslims
hanging out, our Dungans, essentially.
They're called Dungan people now
anywhere outside of China, our our Hui
people back when they looked different
from Chinese people in Central Asia. So,
now they're in Uzbekistan, Kyrgyzstan,
Uzbekistan, and Kazakhstan. These three
places still have these people, Dungan
people, and they speak a version of
Mandarin with Arab words in it, written
in Cyrillic. It's a really magical
language. You guys can search it up. And
they're called Dungan. There was an
altercation in 1862 between a Han person
and a Hui person over who owned a bunch
of bamboo poles for construction. And
the officials sided with the Han people
because they were racist. Because they
were Manchu, Han, Hui, Hui, were all the
way down. It was a lot of racism. This,
on top of the fact that there was a lot
of heavy taxation from the central
government in Beijing because they were
[__] useless at this point. Heavy
taxation, government falling apart, and
the Muslims went "Fuck these guys." and
started a revolt. Now, we call it the
Muslim revolt, but it was actually the
Dungan revolt. So, during the Dungan
revolt and the entire mishmash [__] show
of that area, there was this one man
called the Yaqub was the person that our
man General So was up against. He was a
minor leader, essentially, and he
consolidated power during the Dungan
revolts and had an empire of seven
cities. When they established it, the
English immediately bounced, like signed
up a a commerce agreement with them. And
the Russians bounced, signed up a trade
agreement with them. And de facto gave
this empire international recognition at
the time. And then the central
government went, "Oh, [__] We should
probably do something about this." So,
they asked my boy Zuo Zongtang to deal
with it. So, this guy says, "All right,
cool. I'm going to need my boys." And
his boys were the Hunan Jun, the Xiang
Jun. So, his own dudes. He took a bunch
of spicy dudes from the middle of the
country who grew up in the spicy [__]
tree tropical forests of China with the
no desert training whatsoever and said,
"Let's go, boys." And then he assembled
armies from every racial group he could
get his hands on because his logic was
that this way they have no loyalty, so
they'll fight with no mercy. So, he had
uh Sula. Sula is Manchurian for
leftover. Essentially, bannermen elite
soldiers who didn't have a active post.
So, these would have been noble sons,
young people, old retirees that used to
be soldiers, useless [__] huts. But,
they looked good on the field cuz they
had the best armor and they were
well-fed. About 8,000 of these guys.
Then, 12,000 Ke Lung Jang soldiers
comprised of ethnic Mongols, ethnic
Manchu, the last elite horse archers of
the empire. The These [__] guys. He also
had Xiangjun, he also had uh Chuanyong,
uh more other spicy dudes from the
middle of the basin. Just grunts, spice
[__] that love to fight but with no
equipment. I think a force of 20,000
strong Han or Lü Maoying, uh green army
uh soldiers, which are just ethnic Hans.
And they also had uh surrendered Hui
peoples from previous altercations.
Altogether, a force of 60 to 70,000
soldiers strong to retake the West. So,
he set up good supply lines and pushed
his far armies forward slowly and
steadily, and then retook these cities
one at a time using modern weapons and I
think Krupp German armaments, like
bombardments, big cannons. First time
that the Qing had ever fielded German
armaments on the field. And he took back
the Northwest. 1877 when Yakub, Yakub
Beg, the leader of the khanate, decided
I'm not winning this, and he poisoned
himself or he was poisoned a very
Ottoman way. So, after this, from then
on, uh
my boy Zuo Zongtang decided to call it
Xinjiang, and we still call that to this
day. So, this is not a modern problem.
Racism on our western frontier and in
Central Asia has been a
pan-world problem for way longer than
any of us has been around. If it wasn't
the Ottomans, it was the Greeks. If it
wasn't the Greeks, it was the Romans. If
it wasn't them, it was the Russians, the
Prussians, the English. If it wasn't
those guys, it was us. We were just the
most recent to the party, and
unfortunately, we're now popular during
a time when the internet is most
powerful. So, it's easy to look like the
bad guy. But, this has been a historical
issue shared by many people. So, yeah.
No, that was uh that's the history.
That's why it's called General Tso. I
still have no idea why the [__] chicken
dish is named after him, but there you
go. All right. So, we have our chicken,
and we're now going to go for the second
fry. So, oil goes back inside the pan,
and we're going to re-crispen our
chicken at a higher temperature. While
that oil is heating up, which will take
no time at all cuz I have 10 kilowatts
of power diverting to my stove, I'm
going to take my my shaky sauce and add
a bunch of vinegar, sugar, 20 to 50 g
depending on how American you want it to
taste. Now, as my oil smokes, in goes my
chicken pieces for my second fry. You
want this to be quite violent. You want
the oil to be the temperature around
200-ish degrees, and that's what's going
to give you a very crispy crust,
refreshed and revitalized.
And the best part about having 10
kilowatts is you can actually cook like
a real Chinese kitchen. Override thermal
inertia with just raw wattage. As you
can see, my chicken is really nice and
crispy, separated into chunks, fully
cooked at this point, at which point I'm
going to drain it a second time, and
with the remaining fat in the pan goes
my onion, my garlic, and my ginger, my
dried chili. Give that a toss. Now, you
don't want to cook in earnest these veg.
You just want to toast them
till they're just not raw. So, you want
it to be a half-cooked sort of a veg,
you know? Shiny vegetables, you know?
And in goes your chicken.
Now, in goes my sauce.
Now, if you like more sauce,
make it more liquidous, and then you
make the traditional cornstarch slurry.
If you want more sauce, feel free to
water your seasoning down as you see
fit, but you're going to finish this as
you finish most Chinese-adjacent
foods by adding a cornstarch slurry near
the edge. So, around the edge of the
pan.
And here you have it, General Tso's
chicken. Wow, it doesn't look great, but
it looks fun. Yeah, if you put this on
on some takeout rice, this would be a
great hangover meal. No.
So, yeah, this is it. Feel free to serve
it on top of rice if you so wish, but
this is it.
General Tso's chicken. The actual recipe
from front to back is 20 minutes
maximum. I don't usually make it at home
because as you can see, oil's
everywhere, but this is about as good as
it gets. It is worth making at home.
There's no point in paying 10 US dollars
for [__] this.
No.
Nowhere.
I can't have any more of that. That's
It reminds me of It reminds me of too
many arguments I've had with Yeah, with
all of my colleagues and like with
during my apprentice days where like,
"Hey, do you want to go for Chinese
food?" And they would always ask me,
"So, how different is this from
authentic Chinese food?" I'll be like,
Bro, brother, it's not that it's not
authentic Chinese food. It's that it's
authentic something else. Comment, like,
subscribe. Even if you didn't like this,
comment, like, subscribe because why not
comment, like, subscribe? Then we get to
talk more about history that you don't
really care about next to food that you
also might not care that much about.
But,
I'm happy to do it for you. Talk often
talk soon. Take care, guys. Bye-bye. By
the way, I have nothing against American
Chinese food. I personally think it's
hilarious and sometimes good. Like in
the same way that I think that American
Italian food is hilarious and sometimes
good. There's a reason for it to exist.
It is valid as a food.